A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980 FA739G
Rockefeller Archive Center
- The states and private foundations, talk given before the National Association of Attorneys General, April 16 (Reports 018823), 1975
  Endowments -- Taxation -- Law and legislation
- A commitment to life, commencement address at Miles College, Birmingham, AL, May 24 (Reports 018824), 1965
  "The very existence of Miles College in this community, in this state, at this point in time is fraught with meaning. It is symbolic of the close relationship between freedom and education. It is an inspiring example to people at all stations of life who
- The challenge of Calcutta, address given in Caltutta at a luncheon sponsored by the Indian Chamber of Commerce (Reports 018825), 1968 (Box 890)
  "The people of Calcutta -- the forgotten people -- are not free from hunger, nor are they free from fear. No one would dare argue that they have freedom of mind. But being children of God, it is their right, as citizens of India, to be free from hunger an
  Technical assistance -- India; Charity organization -- India; Ford Foundation -- India
- The changing role of foundations in the South, 20th Annual Conference of the Council of Foundations, New Orleans, LA (Reports 018826), 1969
  "For the South is changing. The forces producing change are many and complex -- some economic, some political, some social and cultural. Some are indigenous to the South and its people; some have been imposed by national policy and an awakened national con
  Social change; Endowments
- The complete text of the speech given at Clinch Valley College (Reports 018827), 1969
  Baccalaureate addresses; Social change
- Human effort planning, School of Journalism, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, N.C., January 26 (Reports 018828), 1970
  "The beginning of every decade gives us the chance to engage in reflection, to assess our values, to look at opportunities and problems, and to indulge in a special kind of New Year's resolutions..." [p. 1]
  Sustainable development -- Planning
- Overview of Appalachia: current ferment, annual meeting, The Commission of Religion in Appalachia, Montreat, N.C., October 29 (Reports 018829), 1970
  "It may be wishful thinking to describe Appalachia as in "ferment", the key word Max Glenn suggested as a focal point for my remarks, but if "ferment" is regarded not as denoting visible agitation but as meaning "at work",-- with ideas and concern and dis
  Social change; Appalachian Region
- The influence of philanthropic foundations, a lake-side talk at the Bohemian Grove, July 26 (Reports 018830), 1954
  "Philanthropy has two major aspects: raising money and giving it away. Most of us, during the course of our lives, have been concerned with both. While raising money we have frequently wondered what characteristics make for success." [p. 1]
- Nitrophosphates and elemental phosphorus in fertiliser manufacture, April 28 (Reports 018831), 1969
  Fertilizers -- India; Agriculture -- India -- Economic aspects
- A strategy for initiating change from within large bureaucratic school systems, March 18 (Reports 018832), 1965
  Education, Urban -- United States; Community and school -- United States; Public schools -- United States; Educational change -- United States; Education -- Political aspects -- United States
- Remarks on the Fund for the Advancement of Education, April 24 (Reports 018833), 1951
  Endowments; Education -- United States; Public schools -- United States; Educational change -- United States
- Lecture -- Towson State College Centennial Lecture Series, Towson, Maryland, November 8 (Reports 018834), 1965
  Universities and colleges -- United States; Towson State College
- Economic development and vocational education, American Vocational Association Convention, Minneapolis, MN, December 10 (Reports 018835), 1964
  Economic development -- United States; Vocational education -- United States
- Vocational education: its place and its process, July 13 (Reports 018836), 1965
  Vocational education -- United States
- Remarks on the origin of the faculty salary problem at independent colleges and ways to ameliorate it, April 12 (Reports 018837), 1956
  Universities and colleges -- Faculty -- Salaries, etc. -- United States
- College admissions developments, November 23 (Reports 018838), 1956
  Universities and colleges -- Admission -- United States
- Speech at the Western States Democratic Conference (Reports 018839), 1962
  "Politics and law are the prescription, and the only prescription. For a guide we may look to the Constitution of the United States, which was established as all here will recall, "to form a more perfect union, establish justice, insure domestic tranquili
  Political science -- United States
- Remarks on the Fund for Adult Education, April 24 (Reports 018840), 1951
  Endowments; Adult education -- United States
- Can we beat the business cycle?, June 23 (Reports 018841), 1954
  Address given before the advertising Federation of America, at the Statler Hotel, Boston, MA.
  Industrial management -- United States
- A businessman looks at health, September 14 (Reports 018842), 1954
  Medical economics -- United States; Medical care -- United States
- Investment in human progress, May 20 (Reports 018843), 1954
- Toward a better understanding, Summer (Reports 018844), 1954
  Three addresses delivered in Europe.
  Competition -- United States; Cartels -- United States; Public opinion -- United States; Social responsibility of business -- United States
- Address at the Annual Dinner of the Poor Richard Club, January 14 (Reports 018845), 1954
  "The United Nations is not a superstate and it cannot -- nor should it attempt to -- do the things which only a superstate might be able to do. But it is a great world forum in which dangerous issues can be forced out into the open light of world opinion,
  United Nations
- Remarks at a "due diligence" meeting of underwriters handling the proposed sale of Ford Motor Company stock by the Ford Foundation, Hotel Commodore, January 9 (Reports 018846), 1956
  Corporations; Stocks
- Statement before the subcommittee on technical assistance programs of the senate committee on Foreign Relations, March 3 (Reports 018847), 1955
  Economic assistance -- International relations
- Investment in tomorrow, March 3 (Reports 018848), 1956
  This occasion is most appropriate for a discussion of what seems to me to be one of the most urgent problems of our American society -- the mounting crisis in education. [p. 1]
  Education -- United States
- Address before the annual convention of the National Automobile Dealers Association, at the Civic Auditorium, San Francisco, CA, January 28 (Reports 018849), 1957
  "Coming events cast their shadows before them, and today our secure and rich land is crossed and recrossed by shadows of events that are yet to come -- events in far-off corners of the world that will inevitably shape our future for better or for worse. T
- Business, the environment and the quality of life, address at the Harvard Business School Public Affairs Forum, Boston, MA, December 2 (Reports 018850), 1969
  "The one thing we can be sure about in discussing the future is that it will be different from the present. I don't know how many of you read the Harvard Business Review, but in the latest issue Peter Drucker observes that the changes between now and the
  Business forecasting; Business planning
- Address before the 36th anniversary meeting of the Associated Industries of Massachusetts, Hotel Statler, Boston, October 25 (Reports 018851), 1951
  "Years ago, the American Road -- all 2,000 miles of it -- was a pretty spotty affair. North and South Main Streets led past the business section, the opera house, the commercial hotel, the library, and the livery stable. It left the residential areas to w
- Address before the Pasadena, California, Chamber of Commerce and Civic Association, February 5 (Reports 018852), 1952
  "Many members of the Foundation organization are not by any means strangers here. But the Foundation itself is a newcomer to this community, and I have had many reports of the friendly way in which you have made our organization welcome." [p. 1]
- Speech given at IITA International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (Reports 018853), 1976
  Endowments -- Africa -- Evaluation; Agriculture -- Africa, West
- Funds, pluralism and the real light on the end of the tube (Reports 018854), undated
  "Were the Ford Foundation always to be the main source for public broadcasting funds, alas, it was for two decades, there such "economic muscle" would be disastrous." [p. 1]
- World without distance: Address prepared for ... the National Association of Educational Broadcasters Convention in Kansas City, Missouri (Reports 018855), 1966
  Keynote speech on the roles of television on education and society.
  Office of the President
  Public television broadcasting; Television in education; Artificial satellites in telecommunications
- Remarks to the National Council of Teachers of English, Milwaukee, WI, November 29 (Reports 018856), 1968
  ...Relevance is simply the interconnection between history and/or literature to what one scholar calls the significant pursuit of the confirmation of today's reality." [p. 2]
- Commencement address at the Stockbridge School, Coeducational International College Preparatory School, Interlaken, MA, June 8 (Reports 018857), 1969
  "Today, the ideals are higher, and they should be. We're sometimes dismayed at the targets of revolt - God, the Army, Presidents of the United States, France, Cornell, Columbia, Harvard, Howard, "Slippery Gulch" and sometimes the head of the Stockbridge S
  Commencement ceremonies -- United States
- Some sober second thoughts on Vice President Agnew, November 21 (Reports 018858), 1969
  Journalism -- United States
- Can Chicago survive its miracles, remarks on Public Television Station, WTTW, Chicago, January 15 (Reports 018859), 1970
  "...Since 1964, the number of commercials on network programming has increased by 50% and on local stations, by far more." [p. 3]
  Journalism -- United States; Public broadcasting -- United States
- Remarks in Indianapolis, Indiana, January 24 (Reports 018860), 1970
  "'Arguments in Indianapolis' was on Murrow's favorite broadcasts, and it was always his hope that someday he could return to Indianapolis - perhaps to participate in a program at the Indiana War Memorial." [p. 1]
  Journalism -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States
- Could the Boston Tea Party be televised, February 25 (Reports 018861), 1970
  "It has become almost a cliche for distinguished jurists to warn that in these times, the Bill of Rights to the Constitution could not be passed by the Congress or ratified by the states." [p. 1]
- Can we managed our miracles, April 11 (Reports 018862), 1970
  "In the late forties and early fifties, the battle over the television spectrum was resolved by such disastrous license allocations that a dozen special studies have been unable to comprehend, much less solve, the problem." [p. 4]
  Journalism -- United States; Broadcasting -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States
- Statement before the Subcommittee on Communications and Power of the House Interstate and Foreign Commerce Committee, April 27 (Reports 018863), 1970
  "The Ford Foundation makes grants for public television. We do so on the basis of proposed plans and financial requirements. The Foundation does not produce programs or operate television stations, or networks. We leave those jobs to the producers, the ed
  Public broadcasting -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States
- Remarks prepared for the National Biennial (Reports 018864), 1970
  "In recent months, what has changed is not the content of the news story, but the agenda set for the reporter. American journalism has become so busy defending its honor against attack from all sides that it has too often followed the news budget chosen b
- Statement before the Board of Estimate, City of New York, July 23 (Reports 018865), 1970
  "Although the June 17, 1970 letter to the Board of Estimate from the Director of Franchises and the Corporation Counsel regarding the proposed contract between Manhattan Cable Television, Teleprompter and the City, makes constant references to the Task Fo
  Public broadcasting -- United States; Broadcasting -- Law and legislation -- United States
- Sam, September 11 (Reports 018866), 1970
  Eulogy of Sam Standard.
- Sam, October 28 (Reports 018867), 1970
- Remarks to the Public Relations Society of America, November 16 (Reports 018868), 1970
  There is a credibility gap -- and as we observe the first anniversary of the Vice President's attack on the news media it is ironic that the poison-tipped arrow he aimed at an institution almost as crucial to the democratic process
  Friendly, Fred W; Press -- United States; Journalism -- United States
- Remarks to the Guilford County Dinner, Greensboro, NC, January 5 (Reports 018869), 1971
  "On that night in April 1908 when, in a small poplar log house on Polecat Creek, Egbert Roscoe Murrow was born, there was a fittingly dramatic event in the Greensboro public library. A professor named W. C. A. Hammel delivered a lecture on a new invention
  Friendly, Fred W; Press -- United States; Journalism -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States
- Commencement address, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI, June 14 (Reports 018870), 1971
  "...The vice president, in fact, would have you believe that some kind of Gresham's law seem to be operating -- that "bad news drives out good news." It is true that there is an abundance of disturbing news on television and in newspapers today, but, cont
  Friendly, Fred W; Baccalaureate addresses -- University of Wisconsin -- United States; Press -- United States; Journalism -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States
- Remarks at the Public-Cable Seminar, National Education Association, Washington, D. C., May 5 (Reports 018871), 1972
  "Ever since the first cat's whisker radio receiver, America has been fast talking itself through the communications revolution. Whether it be radio, color television, or satellites 25,000 miles in space, or the wired nation, we have permitted a tug-of-war
  Friendly, Fred W; Telecommunication -- United States; Public broadcasting -- United States
- Remarks prepared for delivery at the National Press Club, June 1 (Reports 018872), 1972
  "'We (the press) may be a nuisance, but (we) are not a menace. And the way power is running to the President it would be unwise...to concentrate too much on weakening whatever influence we have left.' James Reston said that in 1966 with the administration
  Friendly, Fred W; Broadcast journalism -- United States; Freedom of the press -- United States; Government and the press -- United States
- The spirit of '76 and the next president of the United States -- remarks prepared for delivery at the Washington University Symposium on Politics and the Media, St. Louis, MO, December 6 (Reports 018873), 1972
  The disaster of the 1972 election was that Richard Nixon won and George McGovern lost- that's for history to decide -- but that sixty-three million of the one hundred and thirty-nine million eligible voters stayed home. [p. 2]
  Friendly, Fred W; Journalism -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States; Freedom of the press -- United States; Government and the press -- United States
- Remarks prepared for delivery at the Memorial service for Michele Clark, Rockefeller Chapel, University of Chicago, December 17 (Reports 018874), 1972
  "In the autumn of 1970 when Michele completed her ten weeks at Columbia, a Chicago newspaper ran a two-column picture with the following caption: "Pretty Michele Clark is the newest addition to the news department at WBBM-TV." [p. 1]
  Friendly, Fred W; Memorial service
- The attempted politicalization of broadcast journalism -- remarks prepared for delivery at the Silver Anniversary Banquet of the Northwest Broadcast News Association, Minneapolis, MN, February 2 (Reports 018875), 1973
- Remarks prepared for delivery at the Armstrong Awards, Washington Hilton Hotel, Washington, D. C., March 24 (Reports 018876), 1973
  "Mr. Armstrong, that American original, that man of vision and "high fidelity" was a casualty of that growing American flaw which slowed down FM for a decade, which maimed UHF in the plundering of the valuable electromagnetic spectrum and which threatens
- 60 minutes: "Public television", March 25 (Reports 018877), 1973
- Remarks prepared for delivery before the American Society of Magazine Editors, Plaza Hotel, New York, May 24 (Reports 018878), 1973
  "Journalists and other defenders of a free press are fond of quoting from Mill, Milton, Madison, Brandeis, Holmen, and Hamilton in his plea for Zenger. There ringing pronouncements have their obvious truths, but it might well be that better shelter can be
- Reporter's privilege law: shield of Damocles?, August 6 (Reports 018879), 1973
  "Our two professions, the law and journalism, seem to be on a collision course. The practitioners in the courtroom and the newsroom appear oblivious of each other's mission and determined to ignore the mutual necessity of the First and Sixth Amendments."
- National Hadassah Convention, Denver, CO, August 27 (Reports 018880), 1973
  "Does the citizen know when his news is biased, over-simplified, short-weighted, omitted or otherwise flawed? Is he aware of the economic limitations structuring the newspaper he reads or the television programs he views? Does the consumer realize how the
- Counselor-at-law or gun for hire? -- prepared for delivery at the Practicing Law Institute Seminar on the Communications Law Explosion at the Sir Francis Drake Hotel, San Francisco, Ca (Reports 018881), 1973
- The nervous breakdown of the First Amendment, January 18 (Reports 018882), 1974
  "The public despairs of finding where rights, privileges, special interests, begin and end when the right to fail serves as defense for the self-given privilege to be careless with a public trust, when the right of free speech and the rights of the press
- The love and need of Sam Standard and Philip Randolph Lee, February 13 (Reports 018883), 1974
  "When Sam Standard died in this vital hospital where he had worked and taught, I predicted in a eulogy that we would spend the rest of our lives talking about him." [p. 1]
- Statement before the Joint Committee on Congressional Operations, April 9 (Reports 018884), 1974
  "My unflattering question to this committee on your colleagues is -- have you let Mr. Jefferson down, have you permitted technology and the natural inclination and central motivation of Presidents to move "the great commanding theatre of this nation" to t
- Prepared for delivery at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University, Medford, MA, April 25 (Reports 018885), 1974
  "Once Ed Murrow did a broadcast with Carl Sandburg. In the opening he showed a shelf of all the poet-historian's 28 masterworks: the six volume "Lincoln" -- the Prairie Years, War Years, "Chicago Poems," "Always the Young Strangers," "Remembrance Rock," "
  Friendly, Fred W; Journalism -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States; Freedom of the press -- United States
- Conflicts between the law and the media, June 7 (Reports 018886), 1974
  "It has never been smooth sailing, but what used to be called the fair trial/free press problem has become the Constitution v. the Constitution with the journalist fixed on an unwavering First Amendment course while the jurist sees the bearing as clearly
- Impeachment and trial?: test for the President and television -- commencement address for the Medill School of Journalism, Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, June 15 (Reports 018887), 1974
  To maintain freedom in a rocking boat -- reliable information is crucial. In desperate hours the journalist's task is to provide a picture of reality on which men can act" to take bearings and sightings -- to detect the immediate reefs and shoals; to per
  Friendly, Fred W; Baccalaureate addresses -- Northwestern University; Journalism -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States; Freedom of the press -- United States; Government and the press -- United States
- Remarks prepared for delivery at the dedication of the School of Communication Complex, University of Texas, March 14 (Reports 018888), 1975
  "For a profession that presumes to be the central communications system of a nation struggling to maintain its "freedom in a rocking boat," journalism has never quite managed to explain its mission." [p. 1]
  Friendly, Fred W; Dedications; Journalism -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States; Freedom of the press -- United States; Government and the press -- United States
- The courtroom v. the newsroom -- a conflict and proposal, May 13 (Reports 018889), 1975
- Remarks on the dedication of the Rogers Communications Center, Fifth Annual Membership Meeting of the Public Communication Foundation for North Texas, September 18 (Reports 018890), 1975
  Friendly, Fred W; Dedications; Journalism -- United States; Broadcast journalism -- United States; Freedom of the press -- United States
- John Meredith Patterson -- St. Paul's Chapel, Columbia University, December 17 (Reports 018891), 1975
  "At 6:30 December 8th, when John Patterson died at the Veterans Administration Hospital in West Haven, Connecticut, the current value of a Master's Degree at the Columbia Graduate School of Journalism depreciated by approximately 20%." [p. 1]
  Friendly, Fred W; Memorial service; Journalism -- United States; Journalism, School -- Columbia University
- A new world of public television -- WCET Dedication Banquet, Cincinnati, June 2 (Reports 018892), 1975
  Bundy, McGeorge -- Speeches, addresses, etc.; Dedications; Public broadcast -- United States
- On judging the judges, March 20 (Reports 018893), 1978
  Friendly, Fred W; Judges -- United States; Judges -- Selection and appointment -- United States
- Judges before the court of public opinion, June 8 (Reports 018894), 1978
- The golden age of dissent and the Oregon connection -- commencement address for the University of Oregon, Eugene, OR, June 11 (Reports 018895), 1978
  "No one ever said democracy wasn't a dangerous way to live, only that it was superiou to all the other options. Visitors to our shores are sometimes appalled at how far we carry the concept that government cannot restrain freedom of expression." [p. 2]
  Friendly, Fred W; Journalism -- United States; Freedom of the press -- United States
- Remarks prepared for delivery at the American Jewish Congress in honor of Floyd Abrams, June 21 (Reports 018896), 1978
- Near v. Minnesota -- a half century later, October 21 (Reports 018897), 1978
  "Although journalists tend to give all credit to the Founding Fathers for freedom of the press, it was the creative work of this century's judiciary -- Charles Evans Hughes, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Louis D. Brandeis, among others -- that nationalized the F
- Appointment in Samarra -- in Nebraska, April 16 (Reports 018898), 1979
  Everyone knows there is a running conflict between judges and journalists over the sensitive balance between an accused person's constitutional guarantee of a fair trial and a journalist's constitutional license to report what he sees. [p. 1]
- The Abingdon Conference on political extremism, the media and the law (Reports 018899), 1979
  "For better or worse, each of the sixty seminars that the Ford Foundatin has sponsored in partnership with major news organizations such as the BBC or the New York on Hindustani Times has begun with a not too brief welcome from me laced with an anecdote o